YOUTUBE TRACK MANAGER

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.

YouTube Track manager works with external sources like last.fm and MusicBrainz and loads YouTube links or media library tracks in album, top tracks, chart or radio styles


ALBUM MANAGER

Load and play albums, singles etc
Load and play top artist tracks
Load and play top similar tracks
Load and play top 40 singles chart


AUTO-PICK "RADIO MODE"

Offers custom radio stations with artist, genre/tag, similar artists and similar songs playback, and helps to discover new music 


NOWPLAYING PANEL

Shows:
YouTube videos
Artist, cover or YouTube images
Track & radio info


TRACKS

These can be:
Exclusively YouTube tracks
Available media library tracks else YouTube tracks
Exclusively media library tracks


SOFT PLAYLISTS

Create Soft Playlists of media library tracks


REQUIREMENTS

Spider Monkey Panel 1.2.1+
foo_youtube (any working version)
IE9 or later


INSTALLATION

Add a Spider Monkey Panel to the layout in the usual way. Click the Spider Monkey panel (or right click and choose configure) to open the editor. Use the File menu to import the YouTube Track Manager script

In foobar2000\preferences\shell integration, it's recommended to uncheck "Bring to front when adding new files" to ensure that foobar2000 doesn't grab focus away from other applications


UPDATING

Shift + right click and choose configure. Use the File menu to import the new version 


OPTIONAL COMPONENTS

a) m-TAGS (foo_tags) 1.13+. m-TAGs can be used as a container when compiling albums. This offers several extra options: 1) Enables albums containing YouTube tracks to be added to the media library (requires that the save location is monitored); 2) Enables automatic replacement of YouTube links that no longer exist on YouTube with new ones; 3) Allows media library tracks to be preferred over YouTube tracks while retaining correct album grouping and metadata in the compiled albums. Album track lists from MusicBrainz and last.fm are employed

b) A playback statistics engine or a rating system is recommended for optimal performance of the library radio in "MySelect" mode. This can either be foo_playcount 3.02+, Spider Monkey panel (if you use it for playback stats), a manual rating system, DADA Auto-Rating or other autorating method. Titleformat fields used can be defined in panel properties


USAGE

This section describes key usage. If more information is required, see after this section or search for key words

Radio

Right click, choose "New Radio..." & select a music style. Comprehensive options are available. Last.fm radio loads YouTube links by default; set on "Options\Library" menu to prefer media library tracks. iSelect & MySelect radios are both Library Radios and don't use YouTube. The former filters for tracks in last.fm top tracks lists & can be used to create Soft Playlists. The latter uses a chosen music style, such as similar artists, or a query, to create a pool of media library tracks; how tracks are picked from the pool can be set, e.g. favour highest rated or most played (right click > new radio > tracks)

Top tracks (e.g. top 50) / top 40 chart

Right click & choose "Load..."; set on "Options\Library" menu whether to prefer media library tracks

Albums

Set album manager mode with "Last.fm" / "MusicBrainz" button. Album manager displays albums & tracks of playing artist, unless alternative typed or pasted. Left click an album or track to load YouTube link(s); set on "Options\Library" menu whether to prefer media library tracks (some options require m-TAGS)

In MusicBrainz mode, alt + left click opens the release group at the site

Nowplaying Panel

"Prefer Video", "Image" and "Text Only" modes 

"Prefer Video" mode offers auto fall back to album art / artist photos (+/- text), if no video 

Status button shows mode:
    yT - YouTube Track Manager Text mode
    yI - YouTube Track Manager Image mode
    yV - YouTube Track Manager Prefer Video mode

Set mode with mouse:

Status button:
    Left click: toggles "nowplaying" vs "album manager" display
    Middle click (nowplaying panel): toggles "Video" vs "Image" mode

Image / Text:
    Left click Image: toggles display of cover or YouTube images vs artist photos or info type
       Left click Text: toggles info type, e.g. Artist & Title vs Radio Station Name 
    Middle click: toggles show / hide text

Middle button actions are also on "Options\Nowplaying" menu

External & embedded images are supported. Various image enhancements are available: border, circular, reflection, shadow and smooth transition effects (menu: "Options\Image")

During radio station and Soft Playlist searches the info automatically changes to show the feedback
      
"Prefer Video" mode: video player set up

The foo_youtube video player popup is employed. Position the popup over the nowplaying album art. Album art auto-hides when a video is playing

For best results, in "foobar2000\Preferences\Tools\Youtube Source\Video", set both "show automatically" and "hide automatically" to "Never". On the popup right click menu enable "Zoom: Fixed", "Window: Lock relative to main window" & "Window: Show video only"

As the foo_youtube video player can't be embedded in Spider Monkey panel, the above works by overlaying the popup version. Since it's a popup panel, it doesn't resize with foobar2000. Rarely, it may be necessary to click the foobar2000 main menu item: "View\Visualizations\Video" to reset the video popup display. To avoid that, the panel property "ADV.Video Popup Control..." can be set to give YouTube Track Manager full control. This disables "View\Visualizations\Video" menu functionality and works well if video popups are only wanted while the YouTube Track Manager now playing panel is visible in foobar2000

Alternatively, switch off "Prefer Video" mode (yV) and put the video in its own panel

Touch control (menu: "Options\Mode")

Layout Auto Adjust (panel properties)

Can be used to change the info position in "Video" and "Image" modes

"Text Only" mode: enable in panel properties ("Nowplaying Text Only")


Panel properties

Further options are in panel properties (accessed from the right click menu).

*** ALWAY ENSURE COMMA "," SEPARATORS ARE RETAINED WHERE USED IN PANEL PROPERTIES ***

If you break a panel property, it can be reset by delete -> apply. System panel properties mostly store the menu settings, and shouldn't need to be changed

Availability of custom icons may depend on fonts installed. The icon font can be set in panel properties. Font symbols can be pasted in. Recommended icon fonts are: Segoe UI Symbol, Segoe MDL2 Assets, FontAwesome, Guifx v2 Transports and Wingdings series. The vertical offset & gap provide small adjustment sufficient for fine tuning icon position 

Optionally you can specify your own api keys. If you use your own api keys, script limits don't apply. Paste api keys into panel properties:

"ADV.API Key YouTube"
"ADV.API Key Last.fm"


GENERAL CONFIGURABLE OPTIONS IN PANEL PROPERTIES OR FOOBAR2000 PREFERENCES

Sizes

Album manager font size: set with default user interface or columns user interface list font or use mouse-over with CTRL + mouse wheel to zoom the font size (zoom resets if user interface list font size changed). A custom font can also be set with "CUSTOM COLOURS/FONTS" in panel properties. Use has to be enabled. Any font entered will then take precedence. Nowplaying panel font: set with "Nowplaying Font..." in panel properties. Button sizes: fully scalable - use CTRL + Mouse Wheel over the buttons to change size (can be reset by deleting "Zoom Button Size (%)" from panel properties). Tooltip font size: set with "Zoom Tooltip (%)" in panel properties

Colours

Set with default user interface or columns user interface colours. With columns user interface the highlight colour is mapped to the inactive selected item colour. Panel properties also has a full set of "CUSTOM COLOURS/FONTS" options, that gives control over all the colours used. Their use has to be enabled. Any colours entered will then take precedence 

Titleformat (Web Search) [panel properties]: set for artist, genre & title as required

ADV.Library: Query Fields [panel properties]

Change if required. Default: ARTIST FIELD,Artist,ALBUM FIELD,Album,GENRE FIELD,Genre,TITLE FIELD,Title. Fields are searched in "Prefer Library Tracks", iSelect & MySelect modes using query syntax or similar. This requires simple field names for multivalue tag support. Consequently, titleformatting isn't supported here. Example: if "Band" is used instead of "Artist", change to: ARTIST FIELD,Band,ALBUM FIELD...
 

Add locations method

The default method is the Spider Monkey panel plman.AddLocations. The foobar2000 add locations method can be used instead (set in panel properties: ADV.Add Locations...)


RADIO

Open an Artist, Genre, Similar Artists or Similar Songs radio station based on the playing or selected track

Search for an Artist, Genre/Tag, Similar Artists or Similar Songs Station

In addition to playing music according to taste, the last.fm radio mode is useful for music discovery. Library radio modes offer new ways of playing your own music with weighted auto-picks & avoidance of YouTube tracks

The radio logs played tracks and artists. The aim is that a track shouldn't repeat within 100 (or radio pool size if lower) and multi-artists styles shouldn't repeat an artist within 5 tracks, if possible

The default setting as installed is already optimised and so there is no actual need to change any of the radio settings - just choose the style of music. But options are available as described in the following

Radio switches on and off automatically. The default radio playlist name is: "Radio"

Radio is on whenever "Radio" playlist is used and there is a valid radio source; untick "Auto Radio" in the "Options\Radio & Sources" menu item to have this playlist behave like an ordinary playlist. In any playlist other than "Radio", radio mode is automatically turned off, and so this setting can just be left ticked except in the following usage scenario. If more than one instance of YouTube Track Manager is present, ensure "Auto Radio" is only ticked in one instance

By default the number of tracks in the "Radio" playlist is fixed (default limit = 5; max limit = 25*; adjust in panel properties: "Radio Playlist Track Limit 2-25") with played tracks removed. Untick "Radio Playlist: Remove Played Tracks (menu: "Options\Radio") to disable this behaviour - tracks will then not be removed. *If you use your own last.fm & YouTube api keys the limit is removed and the panel property changes to "Radio Playlist Track Limit 2+"

Menu has "Favourites" list with auto or manual management of up to 30 favourites. Untick "Auto Favourites" to show manual management options. The settings for artist variety, track selection and radio mode will be used when opening an item from the list

The nowplaying panel text shows the pool size of tracks being used to generate the radio station. Pool sizes vary depending on the station type, track popularity & artist variety settings, the number of popular tracks of the constituent artists, advanced settings, and, for the library radio, those in the library and the partial match settings employed. Pool sizes for last.fm radio similar artists and "genre/tag" [Top Artists method] are estimates due to the dynamic algorithms used and refine as more tracks are played 

SEARCHING REQUIRES VALID NAMES, IN PARTICULAR YOUTUBE PLAYLIST ENTRIES MAY LACK ARTIST NAMES, HAVE INCORRECT ARTIST NAMES AND DO NOT HAVE GENRES

Last.fm Radio

YouTube Track Manager uses its own algorithms to manage track selection based on popularity data from last.fm and offers a number of presets, with the names providing a guide as to what tracks to expect: Highly Popular | Popular | Normal | Varied | Diverse | Highly Diverse. These presets progressively decrease the proportion of popular tracks and increase diversity. If the tracks are not popular enough or too popular, it's easy to choose a different preset from the menu, or change the settings of existing presets as below. The default is popular

Artist variety can be set up to a maximum of 250 with top matches returned according to the number set. Lower values favour music most similar to the seed & higher values artist discovery. Default: 50. Optimum: 10-125 for most seeds 

Presets are configurable by editing "ADV.Radio TopTracks Feed Size: Artist 5'Hot'-1000" in panel properties to give greater control over artist song variety
  - just change the numbers to alter the setting. Range 5 (Most Popular [Hottest]) - 1000 (Most Diverse)
    - Default "Artist" feed sizes are 25, 50, 75, 100, 150, and 200 for the highly popular, popular, normal, varied, diverse and highly diverse presets, respectively. "Artist" values apply to each artist of "Similar Artists" and "Genre/Tag" Top Artists styles. "Genre/Tag" Top Tracks & "Similar Song" feed sizes are separately set in "ADV..." panel properties; defaults are higher as these are single lists. The script caps maximum feed sizes in line with last.fm limitations, to 1000 for "Genre/Tag" + "Artist" top Tracks and 250 for "Similar Songs" 

For single "Artist" radio a minimum auto-pick range of top 50 applies to maintain reasonable variety. Apart from this, a top 10 radio etc can be configured 
  - add, remove and rename presets
  - be sure to retain the general structure of the array: each name and feed size should be comma separated; to reset to default, delete the entry from panel properties; commas "," are not allowed in names

Last.fm Radio Options (menu: "Options\Radio & Sources"):

Genre/tag radio: two methods are offered 

- Top Tracks (default) uses the top tracks for the genre/tag as listed by last.fm (tag.getTopTracks). Applies the "Genre/Tag" Top Tracks feed size set in panel properties according to the preset. Although limited by the feed size (max 1000), this method provides an excellent track selection. To have more presets use the max 1000 feed size, increase the feed multiplier. Last.fm similar songs work in the same way (last.fm size limit is 250)
- Top Artists method gets top artists for the genre/tag (tag.getTopArtists) which then enables picking from the whole of each artist catalogue for greater variety. This works like "Similar "Artists" with the "Artist" feed sizes applying to each of the constituent artists. If the tag is a date all tracks of artists active during the specified period are used. To restrict to tracks within the date span use the first method. 
- Both methods work with any valid last.fm tag like genre, e.g. rock, or years e.g. 2015 or happy.

Choose popularity type: current or overall

Current popularity favours songs that are hot and trending right now and increases the frequency of tracks from new releases. Overall popularity will pick tracks according to their all-time popularity - the album manager last.fm top tracks list uses this method. Choosing current popularity will have less impact on established artists lacking new releases or when used with the more diverse presets 

Choose artists selection mode

The default is to play artists of higher similarity more frequently to give a mostly similar music blend and retain a discovery aspect. The alternative is a random pick

Library Radio

The library radio avoids YouTube links and will work best where you have a reasonable number of tracks to pick from (the nowplaying panel reports the pool size)

Two modes are available. Both offer single artist, genre/ tag and similar artists styles of playback with the iSelect mode also offering the similar songs style of playback. Both "genre/tag" methods are supported ([Top Tracks] & [Top Artists]); set on the "Options\Radio & Sources" menu

Use right click > new radio menu to enable the radio mode and choose from options

iSelect (library radio)

This offers internet based selection of tracks from the media library. The library is filtered for tracks in last.fm top tracks lists. Last.fm playcounts and in-built algorithms are employed to bias towards playing the better tracks. This mode avoids the need to have foo_playcount installed to auto-pick library tracks based on track popularity data 

As always, if the tracks are not popular enough or too popular, it's easy to choose a different preset from the menu

To see the search progress, use the nowplaying panel (toggle with status button). iSelect radio loads, and can be played, as soon as there are enough tracks. Any outstanding searches are added in the background. Last.fm lists are cached so search speed should improve as local copies are used. Library analysis is optimised to find matches without duplicates

MySelect (library radio)

Set up as follows
1) Select a media library track pool. foobar2000 query syntax is supported, as well as creating pools from "Similar Artists**", "Genre" [Top Artists** & Top Tracks] and a single "Artist"
2) Decide how to play tracks from the pool, e.g. favour highest rated, plays highly rated tracks more frequently than lower rated and favour most played, plays favourites based on play counts more frequently. Bias level can be changed if required (panel properties ["ADV Radio Best Tracks Bias..."]). Data can be provided by foo_playcount 3.02+, Spider Monkey panel (if you use it for playback stats), a manual rating system, DADA Auto-Rating or other autorating method etc
3) Apply a library filter for a bigger boost, if required, e.g. %rating% GREATER 1 or %play_count% GREATER 4. To enable: right click -> options -> library -> filter. Filter menu is customisable (panel properties ["ADV.Library Filters MySelect..."])

Titleformat for play count and rating can be defined in panel properties ("Titleformat..."). Defaults use foo_playcount fields

Rating can be flexibly set, enabling use of DADA Auto-Rating or other autorating methods, e.g.
%rating% - used by foo_playcount database
$meta(rating) - rating tag value
%jsp_rating% - used by Spider Monkey panel playback stats
%_dynamic_rating% - used by DADA Auto-Rating
%_autorating% - used by other autorating methods

**Artist variety sets the target number of artists. "Genre" [Top Artists] is independent of the music file genre; "Genre" [Top Tracks] uses your own genre

Stations will only open if sufficient matching tracks in library. Console confirms search method

Similar songs radio N/A with "MySelect" mode (grayed out)

Library radio overrides library options for last.fm radio
 
Radio names

These can be changed and personalised by editing the panel property "Radio Names...". Default names are: "Last.fm ,Radio,iSelect ,Radio,MySelect ,Radio,Separator, ∙ ". Each is a consecutive pair of values that are differently used, with the separator at the end


SOFT PLAYLISTS

iSelect library radio can create Soft Playlists of last.fm top tracks found in the media library, from the lists it uses. These are last.fm related playlists, sorted by last.fm playcount, and like those created by foo_softplaylists. You can then play them in any order you like. Soft Playlists can be created for top tracks of an artist, top tracks of a genre or certain tag, top tracks of similar artists and top tracks similar to a song.  Flexible options plus the favourites menu applies

To create Soft Playlists use the right-click menu to:
(1) Set "New Radio...\> Radio..." to iSelect / Save Soft Playlists
(2) Choose the music...
(3) By default Soft Playlists activate on create; this behaviour can be changed in panel properties

To see the search progress, use the nowplaying panel (toggle with status button). Caching of last.fm tracks should improve speed and robustness. iSelect radio still creates and is available 

The Soft Playlist normally creates as soon as the search is complete. A configurable timeout (panel properties: "ADV.Radio Search Timeout...) operates to save the Soft Playlist if the search doesn't complete in a reasonable time. The default is 120 seconds. This is the time without a response from last.fm and aborting the search. As cached copies of last.fm top tracks become used search times should improve


RADIO & SOFT PLAYLISTS – ADVANCED SETTINGS

Genre/Tag: menu items

The "Genre & Tag" menu can be customised in panel properties ("ADV.Radio Genre Menu" & "ADV.Radio Tag Menu"). Ensure comma "," separators are used between the items to be shown on the menu. Tags can also be searched by typing in the "Open Tag Search..." on the same menu 

Feed type: full vs refined

By default, last.fm feeds are refined, where required, before usage to give better track pools. Use of refined feeds is highly recommended for last.fm radio and recommended for iSelect radio and Soft Playlist creation. It's a dynamic algorithm that operates as required

***It may yield small variations in pool sizes for each load***

Set in panel properties: "ADV.Feed Full-0 Refined-1". TopTracks feeds are not used with MySelect radio

If tracks are not popular enough or too popular, or Soft Playlists are too short or long, it's easy to choose a different preset from the menu

To always build iSelect radio and Soft Playlists from full set last.fm feed sizes, set "ADV.Feed..." in panel properties to "full" for iSelect Radio/SoftPlaylists. Soft Playlists created will then be like those produced by foo_softplaylists 

Refine method

This uses an algorithm that blends feed size limits, popular track playcount definitions, relative playcounts and other checks and methods to optimise track selections commensurate with the preset. Popular track playcount definitions can be set in panel properties:

"ADV.PopularTrack [AllTime] LfmPlaycount". Used by iSelect radio, Soft Playlists and last.fm radio in "All-Time Popularity mode". Default is 500,000 all-time last.fm playcounts (album manager last.fm top tracks list displays all-time last.fm playcounts)

"ADV.PopularTrack [Current] LfmPlaycount (6mth)" Used by last.fm radio in "Current Popularity mode". Default is 10,000 last.fm playcounts. Value is over a 6 month period

Default popular track playcount definitions are designed to work well across a spectrum of music. Values act as targets to aid track selection and along with relative playcount calculations are scaled by preset feed sizes

Best Tracks Bias

All radio modes use a "Best Tracks Bias" to select tracks from the pools generated as above. The weighting level can be set between 1 (random pick) and 10-fold (high). All tracks in the pool are available for playing. If the bias is > 1, higher ranked tracks, such as those with higher playcounts or rating, are played more frequently, according to the bias level set

The "Best Tracks Bias" can be set individually for all radio types and radio modes in panel properties (ADV.Radio BestTracks Bias..."). High bias favours highly ranked tracks and low bias diversity. "Best Tracks" are those with highest last.fm playcount (last.fm & iSelect radios) or highest playcount, rating or other parameter (MySelect radio). The bias level affects how tracks are picked from a pool but doesn't change the pool size. If set to 1, there will be no bias towards playing higher ranked tracks and the pick will be random. To change, just alter the numbers. Default settings are already optimised 

Track selection summary

* Last.fm radio, iSelect radio and Soft Playlists *

- Artist, Similar Artists & Genre Top Artists

Feed: set size (per artist; min 50 applies to single artist)
Refine off: whole feeds used
Refine on: feeds reduced for artists having insufficient popular tracks commensurate with preset
Pool: comprises resultant feeds
Radio: weighted auto-pick or random pick from pool, according to BestTracks Bias
Soft Playlist: sorted by last.fm playcount 

- Genre/Tag Top Tracks & Similar Songs

Feed: set size
Refine off or on: whole feed used to generate pool (refinement not needed > single lists predominantly of consistent tracks + feed sizes can be directly set)
Radio: weighted auto-pick or random pick from pool, according to BestTracks Bias 
Soft Playlist: sorted by last.fm playcount 

When lists are refined, reduced lists are dynamically produced and may vary in length for each load. With iSelect radio and Soft Playlists, lists are scanned against the library before loading tracks

* MySelect radio *

All library tracks matching radio type used
Weighted auto-pick according to favoured method, or random pick, according to BestTracks Bias 



ALBUM MANAGER

Album manager can use album track lists from MusicBrainz or last.fm to build albums from YouTube links. Available media library tracks (artist - title match) can be used instead of YouTube tracks. It can also load individual tracks from top tracks lists

Set mode with last.fm / MusicBrainz button

MusicBrainz: search, load and play a wide range of release types including albums, compilations, singles and remixes

Last.fm: search, load and play last.fm TOP albums, TOP artist tracks and TOP similar songs. Shown in popularity order based on last.fm rank, with display of all-time last.fm playcount to facilitate picking best albums and tracks. Drop down menu ("▼") can be used to sort by playcount instead. Last.fm rank is based on number of listeners except for similar songs that use a match score (listeners is not displayed because it is not routinely returned by last.fm)

Buttons to select release type

Click a release to load the tracks: ">" search started; ">>" search processed; "x" no tracks found; if it stays on ">" this indicates that the search could not be completed most likely due to an interruption in internet access. Can choose on the "Options" sub-menu whether to prefer the track list from last.fm or MusicBrainz. If no tracks are found in the first database searched, the second is checked. Because most YouTube entries do not contain album names, searching is by artist – title. This gives the best chance of finding a track but means tracks are representative of but not necessarily the same as the version on a particular release. It also means there may sometimes be omissions, duplicates or incorrect tracks, more so with older/less popular releases due to the nature of searching, YouTube inconsistent naming and absence of some tracks

Middle click an album to load the full album rather than individual tracks. If a middle click is not on an album, it behaves the same as a left button click

Alt + left click of an album name in MusicBrainz mode opens the release group at the MusicBrainz site (status shows ">"); track loading doesn't occur

Releases for the playing artist are automatically displayed. Additionally, artists can be searched. In MusicBrainz mode, live releases and improperly tagged "other" releases are not shown by default even in the "All" "Release Type" since searching YouTube for such tracks mostly works poorly. They can be included for a complete discography in the "All" "Release Type" by enabling the setting on the drop down menu ("▼")

Use panel mode for full album management. Some album management is available in button mode, but releases are not shown since management of long lists is not practical on the menu

Related or similar artists with similarity score are also shown. Related artists are other MusicBrainz search results - useful to change the auto-identified artist. Auto-association with last chosen. Similar artists are from last.fm. Click one of the artists to load releases by that artist. Click the Related or Similar header row to reload the original search artist. Use button ("≡") to toggle mode

"Load...\Albums [Artist]" menu item enables quick access to albums saved by YouTube Track Manager. These may be in the "Album" playlist or media library. Original media library albums are also loaded. A temporary playlist is used: "Albums [Artist] // YouTube Track Manager.


LOAD MENU

> Load top tracks for playing artist or chosen artist. Default is top 50 playlists. Lists are sorted by the last.fm rank order. Note that occasionally YouTube searches may fail for a few tracks and so the list may be less than the target
 
> Load tracks similar to the playing track. Default is top 50 playlists. Lists are sorted by the last.fm rank order. Note that the lists are not available for some tracks. The now playing (artwork/radio) panel provides feedback

> Set playlist size with "Load Menu TopTracks Size 1-50" in panel properties, e.g. Top20, Top40 , Top50, etc. The maximum playlist size is 50 unless you use your own last.fm and YouTube API keys whereupon the property changes to "Load Menu TopTracks Size 1+"

> Load UK top 40 chart. The on-line chart source employed updates weekly on Fridays after ~1900 (UK time) 

> "Load...\Refresh..." menu item is present for refreshing top tracks & top 40 lists when such a list occupies the active playlist


PLAYLISTS

Most playlist names or labels can be configured in panel properties: "Playlist: Names|Labels", "Album,Loved,Radio|Top,Tracks". Just change the names as required. Most names are pretty obvious, e.g. "Radio" = main radio playlist. The "Top" and "Tracks" modifiers are used in "Top50", "Top40" and "TopTracks" playlist names etc. Don't use the string " // YouTube Track Manager" anywhere in playlist names as it is used for auto-management 

Loved and TopTracks playlists can be played in shuffle (tracks) or random mode for a radio style

Use SimPlaylist Manager for easy sorting of playlists -> pop up window (CUI & DUI) or integrate into layout (DUI)

%list_item% can be a useful alternative to %tracknumber% especially with radio or top tracks playlists. Several playlist viewers enable display of columns to be linked to playlist names with support for wild cards, e.g. NG Playlist and el_playlist

Use the main foobar2000 edit menu to further sort, remove duplicates or to clear these playlists. Sort patterns can be edited or added in advanced foobar2000 preferences. Short cuts to these playlists are on "Playlists" menu item


SEARCH ARTIST & MBIDs

Album management and top artist tracks operate with the playing artist by default. Use the integrated album manager search to specify a different artist or song - just click top header artist or song to select, edit, paste (ctrl + v) etc. Auto-searches 1.5 seconds after last key stroke or on enter. Clicking X toggles clearing / reinstating text.  Songs: use | to separate artist and title.  The "Choose" menu available in button mode or by "Shift + right click" does the same thing as the integrated search. Both accept # prefix for directly obtaining artist top50 plus pasted MusicBrainz mbids for artist look ups. The "Choose" menu mode automatically sets according to the album manager view, i.e. artist or song look ups


LOADING ALBUMS INTO THE MEDIA LIBRARY

This offers all the benefit that using the media library offers. Media library viewers can be used in the usual way. To enable:

      1. Install foo_tags (m-TAGS) 1.13 or later.
      2. Set an album build type: "YouTube Tracks"; "Prefer Library Tracks" (use available library tracks else YouTube tracks); original "Library Tracks" (this option depends on tracks being in library). [Menu "Options\Library"].
      3. Set the media library to monitor the foobar2000 profile folder: yttm\albums. m-TAGS files are saved in this location.
      4. It is recommended to add "cover.*" without the quotes to "Preferences\Display\Front Cover", since the script auto-downloads album artwork from last.fm for m-TAGS albums. Depending on download speed, cover display may require a refresh the very first time an album is shown. The console will report if the cover is N/A from last.fm
      5. Click an album in album manager to load

The playlist used is "Album New" [i.e. "New" is appended to the album playlist name]. This playlist is designed to preview loaded albums. Contents are replaced when a new album is loaded. There are loads of albums that work really well, but unfortunately not all - it's best to forget about those and keep the good ones

If the foobar2000 profile folder: yttm\albums is not monitored or "!!.tags" files are excluded from the media library, m-TAGS files will still be auto-created and new albums will be displayed in the "Album New" playlist. They will not show in the media library, but can be played by dropping the saved m-TAGS files into a foobar2000 playlist or by double clicking. Monitoring of the foobar2000 profile folder: yttm\albums can be re-enabled at any time to show the albums in the media library

m-TAGS enables adding albums to the media library and proper grouping/track numbers if referenced tracks originate from the media library. The original media library tracks are un-touched and treated as read-only; track replay gain values are copied. m-TAGS is not used for last.fm top50s, top tracks and top songs; consequently these are not added to the media library. m-TAGs also doesn't support use of media library tracks in container formats where subsong paths can't easily be extracted

Dead YouTube links in m-TAGS are auto-replaced where possible (must have the script default !!.tags suffix). Auto-synchronisation is particularly useful if m-TAGs files are loaded into the media library. m-TAGS are checked daily on playing a new m-TAGS file. Dead library track references can also be auto-replaced where possible (default off) - requires source drive on & media library enabled.  Enable/disable auto-replace in panel properties: ADV.m-TAGS...". Occasionally, if initially try a dead link, try again in a few seconds after it's had time to update

Links in m-TAGS files are automatically checked daily on playing. Any dead YouTube links are replaced with new links. Occasionally, if you initially pick a dead link to play in a new album, the error popup may still occur - please try again in a few seconds after it's had time to update.

By default the script uses a simple check at YouTube to see if the link is available. The simple check doesn't take account of recent changes in region restrictions for particular videos and might occasionally accept videos that are not playable in your country 

A general feature of the script is that it enables automatic generation of m-TAGS, e.g. if you have lots of Frank Sinatra albums and fancy playing "The Best Of Frank Sinatra" that you don't have, this will create and add it to the media library through generation of the m-TAGS file

m-TAGS files can be edited in a text editor; e.g. it is possible to change the video file id used if a different specific one is required (correct the "Duration" in seconds if needed); whole tracks can also be deleted if some are poor etc

Re-loading the album from album manager will replace the existing m-TAGS file. Rename the original if you need more than one version. Ensure the !!.tags suffix is kept. Reloading is also useful if original media library files referenced by m-TAGS are moved or renamed. foobar2000 will show an "unsupported format or corrupted file" error message if links are dead or files aren't found


IDENTIFICATION OF TRACKS IN MEDIA LIBRARY LOADED BY YOUTUBE TRACK MANAGER

Albums added by YouTube Track Manager are saved in m-tags files with the suffix !!.tags. Use !!.tags in filters etc to quickly see those loaded. Any unwanted ones can then easily be removed (e.g. use file operations to delete or move to an unmonitored location). If "view by folder structure" in Spider Monkey Library Tree or the Album List viewer is temporarily used, the files are listed under the initial letter of the artist. They can also be previewed in the "Album New" playlist after loading and if they're not what are required, selected and removed as described above. These methods are much easier to use for deciding what to keep or discard than scrolling through the potentially long album playlist generated when the media library is not used. To block unwanted versions of YouTube tracks, black list them and re-load the album to see if there are better versions

To identify tracks in library or playlist viewers use the following. Symbols etc can be used instead of the text descriptions

$if(%YOUTUBE_TRACK_MANAGER_TRACK_TYPE%, YouTube Track Manager)
- identifies items added by YouTube Track Manager

$if(%YOUTUBE_TRACK_MANAGER_TRACK_TYPE%,$if($strstr($info(@),youtube.com/watch?),m-TAGS - YouTube Video,m-TAGS - Library Track)) - identifies tracks added by YouTube Track Manager and the track type

To view the original media library, use "YOUTUBE_TRACK_MANAGER_TRACK_TYPE MISSING" in filters or "*!!.tags" as an excluded file type in preferences\media library. Enter without the quotes

*** N.B. THE !!.tags FILENAME SUFFIX IS USED FOR AUTO-MANAGEMENT BY YOUTUBE TRACK MANAGER - DO NOT CHANGE IT ***


LIBRARY: TRACK PREFERENCE

This applies whenever "Prefer Library Tracks" is enabled, i.e. library tracks are loaded instead of YouTube tracks. Choose on the "Options\Library" menu item which library tracks to prefer when > 1 track matches the artist - title: "Most Played", "Highest Rated", "Random", "Highest Bitrate", "Lowest Bitrate", "Longest", "Shortest", "Latest", and "Earliest"

The same setting also applies to the MySelect library radio, where it can also be accessed on the "New Radio Station"\Tracks" menu item. The library radio uses the set method for a weighted auto-pick 


MEDIA LIBRARY TRACK MATCHING

The standard match is a case insensitive comparison of the whole artist and title after stripping punctuation + spaces to stop minor interference. Artists are first looked up using an artist IS query and then titles are matched from the returned list

Optionally, partial matching can be used by setting the property "Library: Include Partial Matches 0 or 1" to 1 for the artist or title element(s) required. If partial matching is enabled, the following options are available

- Fuzzy match (applies only to title). Default match 80% 
- RegEx truncation. This is offered because fuzzy matching will not adequately deal with cases where either the library or search data contain extra info like "(feat. artist)". Default RegEx: "\\(|\\[|feat"


When partial matching runs, artists are looked up using an artist HAS query after any RegEx truncation of the artist name

Set partial match methods used with: "ADV.Partial Match: 0 Fuzzy-1 RegEx-2 Both-3" (just change the numbers for the Album, LfmRadio, LibRadio, Top50:40 and TopTracks sources as required). If set to 0, the "Library: Include Partial Matches..." setting is overridden for that source and partial matching disabled for that source. Configure partial match criteria in properties: "ADVANCED.Partial Match Config". Set the fuzzy match % (80% means items need to be 80% similar for a match) and configure the RegEx as required. Note that the RegEx method might not work well with top50s and loading of album tracks because similar track names often need to be discerned (by default partial matching doesn't use the RegEx for these). Set Console to true to output partial match method and results to console 

The RegEx splits the string and returns the part of the string before the first match, e.g. for the default RegEx:
"Rich Girl (feat. Eve)" becomes "Rich Girl"
"The Real Thing [Wendy and Lisa Flow Jam Mix]" becomes "The Real Thing"
"Jenny From The Block featuring Styles & Jadakiss" becomes "Jenny From The Block"

With RegEx, separate options with | (means or). Parenthesis can be used to control order. Escape RegEx special characters, e.g. use "\(" not "(" if literal values are required. It's case insensitive and any unwanted spaces are trimmed. "(\(|)feat" etc can be used instead of the default if specificity is an issue. Omit quotes

Partial matching is not appropriate and not used for MySelect radio due to its nature


YOUTUBE 'LIVE' FILTER

Use to reduce YouTube 'live' versions etc. This is a keyword etc filter applied to the YouTube title & description. Enable/disable in panel properties (default is enabled). It auto-disables if searching YouTube requires a keyword & so should work fine whenever YouTube links are requested. Keywords are stored in the properties "ADV.YouTube 'Live' Filter Title" and "ADV.YouTube 'Live' Filter Description" in regex format. If you're familiar with regex you can edit them, but I suggest checking the specificity of keywords, e.g. use album list filter. The lists for the title and description differ somewhat. More care is needed to avoid false positives with the description. Another good way of avoiding unwanted YouTube versions is to black list them so that YouTube Track Manager doesn't load them in future. This provides full control. It's also a good idea to enable YouTube Track Manager to use the media library if you're only listening to audio ("Options\Library" menu)


YOUTUBE 'PREFERENCE' FILTER

Use to favour certain video types, e.g. "vevo" videos. Enable/disable in panel properties: "ADV.YouTube 'Preference' Filter 0 or 1..." At least one of the available fields: Uploader, Title or Description has to be enabled for the preference to be functional. Recommendation is to check keywords against the Uploader and Title; Description may lack specificity with certain keywords like "lyric". The preference applies to YouTube results pre-filtered for those that match the search criteria (artist & title match, not a full album [unless requested], not blacklisted & not blocked by 'Live' filter) [the "match list"]

Keywords are in regex format (case insensitive), with // as an optional RegEx.Split. Splitters direct searching of the whole "match list" before trying the next keyword. There is no limit to the number of splitters. The foobar2000 console will report syntax errors in custom regular expressions. Examples:

vevo > prefer vevo > return first item containing vevo
vevo|warner > prefer vevo or warner > return first item containing either vevo OR warner
vevo//official > prefer vevo then official > return first item containing vevo; if nothing found re-check "match list" and return first item containing official
audio|lyric > prefer audio or lyric > return first item containing either audio or lyric > favours videos that don't have introductions before the music starts (useful if you just listen to the audio; use just lyric for more lyric versions)
^(?=.*vevo)(?=.*lyric).*$//vevo|warner//lyric > a more complex example > runs 3 checks on the "match list", one after another, since it contains splitters
^(?=.*vevo)(?=.*lyric).*$ > return first item containing both vevo AND lyric
vevo|warner > if nothing found, return first item containing either vevo OR warner
lyric > if nothing found, return first item containing lyric
If no preference is found, the first item in "match list" is returned. Applying the preference filter to the "match list" rather than the whole YouTube search results is necessary to avoid returning wrong tracks that match a preference keyword

If the preference filter is off, the first item in "match list" is returned

If there are no items in the match list the first YouTube hit not blocked by the "Live" filter or black list is returned, or failing that the top YouTube hit. The track is named accordingly. Usually it will be the correct track; it's just that it's not been possible to match the artist - title name. That can arise because of inconsistencies in YouTube naming, e.g. some don't contain the artist name, or the way last.fm names certain tracks

For anyone interested in refining preference keywords, "ADV.YouTube 'Preference' Verbose Log..." can be enabled. This will output the basics of what's going on to the foobar2000 console. The log can be quite long, and I suggest copying and pasting from console into a good text editor or saving the console output to file


MEDIA LIBRARY FILTERING: All Modes

"ADV.Library Filter...". This is a general filter that applies to all modes. Most users should leave this property blank to ensure that the whole library is used. However, it enables certain categories of tracks to be excluded from the library copy used by YouTube Track Manager. Enter a query using the foobar2000 query syntax. Ensure queries are valid and doing what you want, e.g. test with album list filter. Example usage: bootlegs, but not other tracks, have the field %boot%; bootlegs can then be excluded from the library copy used by YouTubeTrack Manager using "boot MISSING" (without quotes). Additionally, MySelect radio has its own filter options that apply only to that mode (see above)
 

SEARCHES

It is not recommended to start new searches or change the playlist while a search is in progress and until all tracks have loaded

POWERED by last.fm, MusicBrainz & YouTube


TRACK MATCHING & NAMING

The YouTube search compares video names found to the search criteria to find the best match. Either YouTube links with the most relevance or views can be favoured (set in panel properties: "ADV.YouTube Prefer Most: Relevant-0 Views-1"). The default is relevance

Tracks are dynamically renamed according to the search details. This facilitates any biography and lyric searches and gives tidy playlists

If a perfect match isn't found, the best match is loaded


FRONT COVER DISPLAY

YouTube Track Manager checks the following and displays the first cover found
1) Front cover search patterns set in foobar2000 display preferences
2) foo_youtube thumbnails [foo_youtube loads these after (1)]
3) Stub image set in foobar2000 display preferences for front cover
4) YouTube Track Manager No Cover image 


ARTIST IMAGE DISPLAY

YouTube Track Manager can automatically fetch artist images from last.fm. For this, set "Image [Artist] Auto-Fetch" to true. The images are saved in the "Image [Artist] Folder Location" set in panel properties. If more than one instance of YouTube Track Manager is present, enable for only one instance. The fetcher is the same as the one in Biography. If you use both YouTube Track Manager & Biography only enable the auto-fetcher in one as the folder location will still be "live" monitored by both (default is disabled in YouTube Track Manager & enabled in Biography). Image menu has black list option to stop display & fetching of unwanted images

YouTube Track Manager checks the following and displays artist images for the first location found
1) "Image [Artist] Folder Location". Checked if "Artist [Image] Cycle" is set to TRUE (default)
2) Artist image search patterns set in foobar2000 display preferences
3) Stub image set in foobar2000 display preferences for artist image 
4) YouTube Track Manager No Photo image

Media library tracks, radio streams and YouTube tracks are all supported

The "Image [Artist] Folder Location" can be customised. This enables changing the auto-fetch download location. It also enables loading and cycling of artist images provided by another plug-in/script

Examples:
foo_uie_biography default: "%profile%\lastfm\artist\%artist%" (change if you used a different location)
marc2003 samples: old location: "%profile%\wsh_data\artists\%artist%"
marc2k3 samples: new location: "%profile%\js_data\artists\%artist%"
YouTube Track Manager default: "%profile%\yttm\art_img\$lower($cut(%artist%,1))\%artist%"

Switch off auto-fetching by YouTube Track Manager if you're using a functional fetcher with another plug-in/script that saves images

To set the "Image [Artist] Folder Location", enter title formatting or an absolute path to a file. %profile% can be put at the start of the path and resolves to the foobar2000 profile folder or program folder in portable mode. As with title formatting, enclose literal ()[]'%$ in single quotes. The last entity in the path defines the folders that contain the artist images - use %artist% or suitable unique alternative 

Don't use %path% on its own or part of another title format expression [e.g. $directory_path(%path%)], in the folder location; they won't work correctly with YouTube tracks and streams

Artist images saved to the "Image [Artist] Folder Location" can be displayed with other artwork and playlist viewers. One image will be picked for each artist. For the default location, example paths you need to put in preferences>display>album art and search pattern for ARTIST are: 

Standard install
C:\Users\YOUR USERNAME\AppData\Roaming\foobar2000\yttm\art_img\$replace($cut(%artist%,1),.,_)\$if($stricmp($cut(%artist%,1),.),_$substr(%artist%,2,$len(%artist%)),%artist%)\*
REMEMBER to enter YOUR USERNAME

Portable install
J:\foobar2000\yttm\art_img\$replace($cut(%artist%,1),.,_)\$if($stricmp($cut(%artist%,1),.),_$substr(%artist%,2,$len(%artist%)),%artist%)\*
REMEMBER to set the correct drive letter and path to foobar2000 

To optimise the image display if required, adjust the relative "Image Size 0 - 1", "Nowplaying Font Max Size" and "Border" in panel properties. The font size set is the maximum that will be used and is scaled automatically with window height and the space below the image 

The YouTube Track Manager artist image fetcher features auto-adding of new images. It initially obtains the top 5 pictures of an artist from last.fm. It will check after every 28 days if the artist is played and if there are different pictures in the top 5 it will add them retaining those already saved. Because it always picks from the top 5, only the better images should be obtained

To use a local last.fm site for image fetching, shift + right click>configure>search for "http://www.last.fm/music/" and change it to the country specific version required, e.g. "http://www.lastfm.fr/music/" for France etc 

Acknowledgements
YouTube Track Manager uses the same last.fm source for artist images as the original biography view component by Senna. Unfortunately that component stopped being able to download artist images a while ago due to changes in the last.fm api. marc2003 then introduced a non-api method for downloading artist images from last.fm. This principle is used herein and adapted for compatibility with YouTube Track Manager and quirks of YouTube tracks with support for radio streams and automatic updating. So thanks and credit to marc2003 for the original method. Also acknowledgement to falstaff for the original nocover image drawing code that is adapted herein


BUTTON MODE

Set button mode in panel properties to true. The panel container can be sized as small as the size of the button (default size 22px 16px). Use the functionality offered by the button menu. Use of button mode in columns user interface works best works with a panel stack splitter container. Position the Spider Monkey Panel with forced layout on the panellist tab and $movepanel in the PerTrack script as per the panel stack splitter documentation. Use of button mode in default user interface works best when positioned to the right or left of a panel of low height, e.g. quicksearch. Only limited album management is available in button mode, since management of long lists is not practical on the menu. Use panel mode for full album management


LOVE \ BLACK LISTING

"♥ Add to Loved Playlist" enables tracks to be easily played again. The simple artist | Title name is shown. Works with YouTube tracks, media library tracks and in fact any tracks including radio streams. Operates with a local playlist - does not send anything to last.fm

Videos can be black listed based on video id number. This will stop album manager and radio playback loading them again, provided an alternative version is found. Often the tracks will be present in the last.fm top tracks album manager view, and can immediately be reloaded from there to test the effectiveness of the black listing. Black listing will not stop the loading of a particular track but just a particular video version. Black listing is managed on the menu where videos can be added or removed/viewed. The " - Remove from Black List" and "View" menu items toggle upon clicking between allowing removal and viewing the black listed videos in YouTube so that black listed videos can be checked. The black list is saved to a file (foobar2000 profile\yttm\blacklist.json). The black list shows the YouTube video name so that different versions can be identified


CACHE

Radio Stations are automatically cached and updated periodically when new data is obtained. The saved data provides a repository for use if last.fm sources are unavailable. Enabling "Radio Play saved Stations" uses saved last.fm data and stops last.fm look-ups. It also sets the menu to show the stations that are available for playing from saved data. This is useful if last.fm is not available, or you wish to play iSelect or MySelect radios, or create Soft Playlists, entirely offline. If you saved Echonest Radio Stations before the demise of the Echonest api, they can be played by setting the panel property "ADV.Allow Playing Saved Echonest Radio Stations" to true in addition to enabling "Radio Play saved Stations"

The "Radio Play saved Stations" settings also apply to artist tracks (e.g. top 50) and top similar tracks (e.g. top 50)


INTERNET ACCESS

Reasonable internet access is required for the searches and to play YouTube tracks. The panels provide feedback on search progress and the console will report errors. Internet searches mostly have a timeout of 30 seconds. Internet searches are only done on demand or if the panel is visible in foobar2000 etc to obtain actual information displayed. They do not run in the background, except if "Image [Artist] Auto-Download" is enabled, whereupon downloading of artist images will occur. Where available, internet explorer cache results are preferentially used


SOUND LEVELLING: REPLAYGAIN AND HOW TO APPLY TO YOUTUBE TRACKS

For playing a mixture of YouTube tracks and media library tracks that have replay gain, consider using DynamicDSP to apply replay gain with the EBU R128 Compressor on the fly to tracks lacking replay gain. This can be done as follows. Install the DynamicDSP v2 and EBU R128 Compressor components in the usual way. In preferences\playback\DSP manager, add DynamicDSP to the list of ActiveDSPs. Highlight and click configure selected. Enter, e.g. $if(%replaygain_track_gain%,,R128Comp) titleformat script in the large textbox at the top of the DynamicDSP configure window; enter the DSP chain name R128Comp in the little textbox to the left of the "New Chain" button then click that button;  click the chain name in the list box and add the EBU R128 Compressor. The EBU R128 Compressor automatically matches to the ReplayGain standard 89 dB using the standard R-128 algorithm and a reasonable look-ahead. The EBU R128 Compressor should be at the top of the DSP chain if other DSPs are included. Some users have reported that using crossfader in DSP (200ms or higher) is helpful


EL_PLAYLIST

If you use el_playlist, it is recommended not to use nodelay in image functions ($albumart, $imageabs or $drawimage) that draw YouTube thumbnails

The synchronous nature of the nodelay flag can cause track additions to be slow

This applies to tracks added directly with the actual foo_youtube plug-in as well as this script


Statement required by YouTube: All YouTube users agree to be bound by the YouTube Terms of Service https://www.youtube.com/t/terms
